[SPEAKER_02]: There's also called origination.
[SPEAKER_02]: It begins very shortly.
[SPEAKER_02]: I will teach you the origination, the pathway, the four extensions of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Listen to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And what it is, is the origination of the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, what I've been going on and on and on and on about, especially in... when I was... when I went against techniques, meditation techniques, by understanding what mindfulness is, you're mindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: By understanding the nature of the phenomena, you're mindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if there is no understanding, then it's not founded in mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by understanding the arising, the manifestation, the nutriment of the body that's simultaneously present with the present body, you are automatically fulfilling the satipaṭṭhāna of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, again, you can only understand that if you have the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just... Yeah, it's just... Yeah, exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the nutriments of the body, body being, say, from looking at the body... Well, basically, you see, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Every experience, unmindful experience, is the experience of, you know, the self-centered point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you are the center for your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything is for you, to you, against you, in relation to you, and you remain the reference point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even when a person thinks about their own body, it's again, it's this body as mine, as a relation to this center that is me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this body is here, and this body gets sick, and this body... but still,
[SPEAKER_01]: He does not question the validity of that assumed center of that experience, which is basically the owner of the experience, and if that experience is the experience of the body, then he's the owner of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: But by recognizing that such a fundamental thing, such as body, for example, taking the phenomenon of the body, is actually not rooted towards this center, but it's actually rooted away from it, in those random neutrinos.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the origination of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you realize,
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize, basically, that even when you're unmindfully appropriate body, even that is impossible to be a genuine appropriation, because the body remains fully impenetrable to you, as a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impenetrable to the ownership by that assumed center.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you have nutrient and the body as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: When that ceases, the body cannot remain a second longer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just presence of this, this is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can even take that in a loose sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can even take that in a completely kind of... the body has been growing... yeah, the body has been growing, growing, growing older, getting bigger, aging, what not, in a course of time, doesn't matter, while the nutriment as a phenomena was present, as availability, as a consumption, as a food and things like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, so which means this body has been maintained,
[SPEAKER_01]: Through that, like, direct dependence, externally, by the nutrient, not by you, in any shape or form.
[SPEAKER_01]: You couldn't have done it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a different direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a completely different direction from the direction of the scent itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And another thing is, I think I said it probably a number of times, maybe in recent talks as well, mindfulness, if done rightly, doesn't come from you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It comes from the discernment of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they arise, they're present, and you use that presence as the presence of mindfulness, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's what mindfulness is, the recognition of presence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever phenomena is present, presence is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by recognizing that those things upon which you are mindful are completely independent of you, that mindfulness is unrighteous, and that's how it becomes satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: By discerning the independence of the body that you have been appropriating,
[SPEAKER_01]: The independence of the nutrient upon which the body directly stands, that you have also been appropriating and consuming, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize you can't appropriate that, and that's where the mindfulness is rooted, in that discernment.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's satipaṭṭhāna, with the discernment of the nutrient.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just discernment of the body, because usually, there would be this self-centered, and then this body, which is still for that self-centered, and then you might contemplate this is not mine, this is... You won't actually land or apply, or take root, because you're still doing it from that self-ass
[SPEAKER_01]: Of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: But seeing that it's rooted, that it's actually coming, that it's true, roots are coming from a completely different direction, direction that you cannot go to, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you will always remain self-centered.
[SPEAKER_01]: You step away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Step below you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, then, then it becomes very different.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then that body can't be yours, even if you're appropriate in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you're not really appropriate in it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the nutrients being food.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I mean, again, again, you can just take a nutrient as a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: That which nourishes something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: That upon which something else is nourished.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter what it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, if you look at foods, just food, say, the possibility of food is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't see the food in relation to the nutrient of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't see the food in relation to being a saṅkhara, to the maintenance of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, like, when a person looks at the food, they just look at it as another thing that they own, that they possess, that they consume, that they appropriate.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's about seeing the relationship.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can find that relationship only through the arising body, only through the body that's being manifested right there, and then, while it's still right there, and then being manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, through the presence of the body, you can discern the presence of the nutriment.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you'll find out that it's that food.
[SPEAKER_01]: That you've been finding a left and right, an up or down, away from the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Through the presence of the body, there is a remunerance of the particular aspects of the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a remunerance for the body, generally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, sure, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, say, like, say, take any, I don't know, a loaf of bread.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's just a loaf of bread, as an object of your experience, that's just an arisen thing, that you can appropriate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Indulge sensually, if you're eating out of pleasure and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if you, through the mindfulness of your body, through the phenomenon of your reasoned body, look for the, like, the phenomenon of food, which is that which sustains the body to be what it is, and then, through that phenomenon of food, so through the body, through the notion of the phenomenon of food, you can look at that loaf of bread.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's still the same loaf of bread, but now it's actually seen in a completely different
[SPEAKER_01]: Timeless context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Timeless, as in simultaneously present context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you're not necessarily eating that bread, right there and then.
[SPEAKER_01]: It shares the nature of the nutriment upon which the whole body, right here and now, that is present, stands.
[SPEAKER_02]: The body can consume itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I say, like, you have to look at it as the phenomenon of nutrient.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter what a content of it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter what the ingredients are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yeah, theoretically, the body can be eating itself and gain nutrients for parts of the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: But when there's no nutrients, there is no body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's no presence of nutrients, presence of that that can nourish the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: The body and nutrients, you can see it's inseparable.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, inseparable.
[SPEAKER_02]: Cannot arise apart from each other.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I suppose that's the reason why the body is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because of these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because of this self-centered, assumed sense of ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, these things are also included, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, plural.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can say plural.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is more plural.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a singular nature of these plurality of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why saṅkhara is like determination.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's kind of plural.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The very body, the most personal aspects of your body that you regard as yours, are actually as external as that loaf of bread, as that jar of milk, as that cast-iron kettlebell, as this piece of stone.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that kind of matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just the matter that's closest to you, and it's also matter because of which you get to see and experience the matter, as in objects of your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because of that, you just assume, assume a privileged position to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's as external as all your sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: You get external.
[SPEAKER_01]: The body is as external as them, as they are.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: You speak about yesterday, but that hollowness, you mentioned before, the hollowness of the body, being either extinct, prevailing,
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know if it will coincide with feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it will, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's not...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the shape of the body is there, the shape of the...
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't resonate with myself.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't resonate with the sound of you.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't think it...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's hollow.
[SPEAKER_01]: The shell.
[SPEAKER_01]: The shell is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not filled anymore with that kind of...
[SPEAKER_01]: The life energy of ignorance, so to speak, which is the energy of appropriation, assumption, upādāna and everything else, the energy of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, it still operates, for as long as the shell doesn't completely break apart.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it's not in a way like...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, it is more subtle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, but you start with the same...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you start with the principle that we just discussed.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a phenomenon on which
[SPEAKER_01]: The phenomenon of the body directly stands.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's being nourished by, it's being determined by, it's being founded in.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the same sense, feelings, it's inconceivable to have a... Again, it's through the presence of feelings you discern contact.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not before the feeling or after the feeling or the other side.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through the presence of...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, while the feeling is enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I keep saying the beginning of mindfulness is the recognition of the persisting while changing aspect of the arisen phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever it's a feeling, you have to learn how to let it endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thoughts, arisen experiences, experience as a whole, you need to basically let it endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Allow it to keep changing while remaining the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you can start seeing things through that sort of maintained persistence of an arisen thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in this case, feelings... if you immediately start, like, there's a feeling, a feeling arisen, and then, you immediately, oh, not mine, not mine, this is not myself, these feelings are just sensations, it doesn't work, there are kalāpas, and whatnot, I don't know, you start... None of that, basically, is found in the mindfulness of that feeling that has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because mindfulness of the feeling that has arisen means allowing feeling to persist on its own, on its own terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether that's pleasant, unpleasant, fearful, dreadful, anxious, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to be able to allow it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because only through that, allowing, you can start discer... That's like recognizing things as phenomena, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Allowing it to arise, for what they want to arise, and for however long they want to arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if the feeling is allowed to arise, through that, then you can start discerning contact.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you could see, what was the nature of the nutrient,
[SPEAKER_01]: In relation to the body, it was something that you could not own.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's something that's always, like, underneath that body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your ownership stops at the threshold of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why body is mine, and then these things are for the body, and whatnot, I for me, and similar.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when you recognize that, no, this body that I regard as mine, actually, directly stands upon other thing than me, not me.
[SPEAKER_01]: It stands upon these things that we can call nutrients.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you see, it's impossible for you to own those nutrients in such a manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your ownership cannot go through the body and take possession of nutrients.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're always going to be a step below you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Below your reach, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as far as you reach, they're going to be a step further than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's how you recognize that you cannot appropriate the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because even if... no matter what sense of ownership you have,
[SPEAKER_01]: That body stands upon these nutrients, which, if they disappear, the body will disappear, and your sense of ownership will disappear.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you stop regarding your sense of ownership as your own, as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now, the second paragraph tells us that the contact shares the same nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't own it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't access it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always going to be a step below you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's important recognition to sort of discern, because people do, and based on the traditional interpretations of contact, you think you can prevent it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think you can prevent contact by shutting your eyes, by turn... you know, closing your ears, turning your head away, walking away.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that body that's thrown out there in the world, based upon these nutrients, subject to these elements, that body is being contacted constantly, for as long as those... for as long as that shell remains.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't stop contact.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can only stop appropriating that which is being contacted, as a result of which, your feelings will be hollowed out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but again, you're thinking about a contact now, and you should, only through the recent feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever feelings you have now, present, presently enduring, through that, you discern, there is that which is contacted.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, you can, if you want to, if you want to pin down contact onto something, you could really just, just, kind of, quite a general designation and say, it is that body that's contacted.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now, the body,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of a nutriment, so to speak, for the feelings to arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: The presence of the body in the world, or even more, slightly more accurately, you can say, the presence of the senses in the world, is the basis for the feelings to arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: The sense experience?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But sense experience not in these senses of mind, but those sense organs in that body that stands upon those nutrients.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why you can't just skip to the second about feeling and contact and forget about the first.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same principle that needs to be built up from the start correctly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, only when you're mindful of the body properly, in that sense, then the content can become apparent as that, that sort of discern through feelings, and further and further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, then later on, once you sort of fully understood that, you become proficient in these four satipaṭṭhānas, and then you don't necessarily have to keep doing them in the same order, but clearly you could see, there's no satipaṭṭhāna without right contemplation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nor, there is a, there is no right contemplation that wouldn't result in establishment of mindfulness or samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't have to, like, okay, so I think this, then I think body nutrients, now I'm going to step two, step three.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just keep drilling the same principle on different levels.
[SPEAKER_01]: First, on the obvious level, body nutrients.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, the same principle on level of feeling and contact.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can really... that's true if you're an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're a practitioner, you say with feeling, there is contact.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you're approaching through satipaṭṭhāna, first you're going to see feelings through which you can discern a contact.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the impersonal, sort of, eh... descriptional way, you would say, yeah, contact is a nutrient for feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, from your point of view, which is the only point of view you have, or which is the only point that you have, you have feelings through which, in the same sense, you have body through which you discern nutrients.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you start... you stop, basically, placing emphasis on the side of body as my body in relation to me, on the side of feelings as my feelings in relation to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you recognize the emphasis is against your will, against your control.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't even conceive to change that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's actually rooted in saṅkhara, in the determinations, not in you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you stop regarding things as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because you want to, but because you realize it's impossible to not not do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you... they are... they cannot be yours, even if you want to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just have to recognize that thoroughly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you start with the body, through which you discern the simultaneous presence of random nutrients.
[SPEAKER_01]: They are not the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start with the feelings, through which you discern there has been contact.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's still there, enduring, because these feelings are enduring.
[SPEAKER_02]: I always want to ask, why is there feeling?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, see, there's... Yeah, yeah, well, yeah, but see, you would ask that because, for you, contact seems... well, it's still regarded as optional.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, you ask, why is it then?
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that you think your question can pertain to the nature of contact means you... you think you can put it in question.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's already a form of accessing it, and owning it, and relating to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can put your feelings in question,
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you look why they are there, you would see because it has been contacted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or contact has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't think of contact as that kind of, I don't know, whatever they describe it in commentaries or like a medical, you know, description of it either.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, think of contact as a manifestation of pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you can say, but I don't think it would shed any more light, because perception already has lots of assumed notions attached to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Think of it as pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can have a very agreeable pressure, which is then felt pleasantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can, again, the reason why I say pressure is because pressure remains for as long as
[SPEAKER_01]: Contact is being felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, feeling is inseparable from contact.
[SPEAKER_01]: You may not necessarily realize all this, only if you're feeling the contact.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, because there is that in the world, that can be pressured, that can be touched, that can be contacted,
[SPEAKER_01]: There is feeling simultaneously present right there in your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is no linear connection that you can observe.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, there is no linear connection between nutrients and the food, because if it were, you were not seeing it as a simultaneously, eh... timelessly present principle of nutrient and that which is being determined by the nutrient.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you would be able to see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you start like a contact, aha, here, and then goes this, and then sensations, and then this is the feeling, that's all out there.
[SPEAKER_01]: None of that is actually what you are feeling,
[SPEAKER_01]: And the pressure that's underneath that feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, take up any feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, you have to start from feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasurable feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is a... there is a agreeable pressure through... found through that pleasurable feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Painful feeling can persist for days, which means, for the whole time, the disagreeable pressure persists.
[SPEAKER_01]: The disagreeable contact has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: The disagreeable contact is being manifested, or rather is manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: The disagreeable contact is persisting while it's changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: The disagreeable contact is enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: The pressure is enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by seeing the pressure and feeling, two different things, but completely inseparable,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you will stop regarding feeling as yours, and then pressure one body.
[SPEAKER_02]: I want to say it's the same thing, but I notice two different things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's not the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is two different things that are simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Together?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can say that they're conjoined, as the Buddha would say, in regard to the perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, they're not the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you cannot think them apart either.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, one is found through the other, through the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, think of feeling, you're already implying pressure within the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just, what I think of feeling, feel the feeling, you're already, there is already pressure within that feeling, while, that's important bit, while, not after or before, but while it is being felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, feeling is inseparable from depression.
[SPEAKER_01]: And same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasurable, very agreeable, delightful feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, it's a very agreeable pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_01]: Neutral.
[SPEAKER_01]: Neutral feeling again, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's basically neutral pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Neither agreeable nor disagreeable pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what contact is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, you'll be much better off thinking of contact in those terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't need to designate it any more accurately.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is quite sufficient, actually, to... because the whole purpose of it is to see that simultaneous dependence, simultaneous relationship of this is being nurtured simultaneously, while it is present, by contact.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you can't own it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not rooted in you.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, by seeing, contact is with feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: Feeling is with...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by discerning contact through the feeling, you automatically stop appropriating feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what the narrator meant when he said, uh, in order to uproot the thing that's been taken as yourself, you have to see it as directly depending upon that which is not at the same time taken as the self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you look at loaf of bread, or if you look at the pressure or contact separately, yeah, you take that as yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You appropriate that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you discern that through the feeling that is at the time then taken as a self by default, then that won't be able to be taken as a self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet you see it as that because of which this that you did take as yourself depends upon.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you realize, well, then I myself am not my own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, that is not self.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you were saying yesterday, otherness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when the feeling is not yours anymore, basically, that that trail of that pressure that has been exhibited on you remains.
[SPEAKER_01]: The depth, you know, the imprint, so to speak,
[SPEAKER_01]: It can persist for a while, but now it's been, well, drained out, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not charged anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no charge to it, because it's not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, it's just a different extent of different amount of hollowing that the pressure has exerted.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense... Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is, arahant is not just like a
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know how to sort of... like, he's not basically completely unaware, unrecognizing of any feeling anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's not a robot.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the significance, the pressure of a certain experience is still very much there, to the extent that he wants to go.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why Arahant is not afraid of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: He cannot even conceive the fear of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't mean because he's not aware what death is.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the contrary,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he's actually the only being that is capable of fully comprehending and grasping the imprint, the pressure of the experience of death, and even that cannot overtake him anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the sense that other feelings, while he's still alive, other pressure that's being exerted, different significances, somebody comes and starts killing all the monks around him and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's not like, oh, what is happening?
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows exactly what's going on and he feels that amount of hollowing towards him.
[SPEAKER_01]: That used to be the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: There used to be that pressure exerted on him.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, he cannot engage on that level.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he's completely beyond it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he still recognizes the degree of that hollowing that used to be felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's empty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Little empty, big empty, but doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's empty.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, little feelings are little empty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Big feelings are really empty.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is the nature of that emptiness, that hollowing, that draining away, disowning, dispassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: All that is just completely extinguishing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, like a hollow stump.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the Buddha who described it.
[SPEAKER_02]: The translation of asa, as touching, or pressure, as opposed to contact, always goes anymore with people.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the idea of, like, like... Who was just stating that then?
[SPEAKER_02]: Somebody, or...?
[SPEAKER_02]: You just did.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah, but I mean, before... Oh, it would just translate as, like, just contact.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then you're confused.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, no, the arahant still has... Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But they're not, in a sense, like, they're in a certain sense, they are not touched, the lyrics, touching, so to say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is that pressure, or following, because he's not pressured anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is, when people think contact, they think of something that has happened, that is done.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not so.
[SPEAKER_01]: You actually discern the contact through the feeling that is right here, happening now, which means contact is right there for that whole time, enduring through it, through the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if there is no that pressure, there wouldn't be any feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize that which is being pressured, it's the level of those nutrients and the level of that body that's not in your control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Excuse me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you can't prevent that pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just completely inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Accessing the domain where the pressure occurs is just... you can't even imagine it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, you know it's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you discern it through those feelings that are being felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you start the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing that body currently.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just getting the grip, the notion of the principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you can start... What's beyond this?
[SPEAKER_02]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_02]: Your mind gets larger and more developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it becomes more discerning of the principle, which means... and that... it's a universal principle that is present in everything that is arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's a universal principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, then, you don't have to keep repeating.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just start seeing it, because, yeah, it's arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, it's partaking to this nature of the same principle that you have understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and even now, like, there was never, like, a special contemplation between feeling and the contemplation of nutrient.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think I might have read that sutra, but I don't even remember it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point is, you look at the principle and you see exactly what's there, and how it has to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: And more skilled people would maybe describe it in even a greater detail, more accurately.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's important is to see the principle, because that's what frees you from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fully developing that is how you become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: With the origination of name-form, there is the origination of mind, the cessation of name-form, there is the passing away of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now that's getting you modifying.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, no matter how refined it gets, it doesn't mean it's getting more intricate or more complex.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is becoming more subtle within the same principle or principle that was pertaining to the first thing that you read, and the second thing, and the third thing, and then the fourth thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is then the next thing that people will regard as mine?
[SPEAKER_01]: You have your body, your feelings, and the next thing would be, oh, my mind, this, this ambiguous presence of this mental energy and whatnot, however you want to call it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's, that's what...
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mental.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the, it's the, it's the closest to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's closer than, more closer than your feelings, and it's more closer than your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how you disown that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, by letting it endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: By seeing it arise and by, through its presence, discerning that upon which the mind has to be standing, which is not you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's name and form.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The world.
Everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything that can possibly manifest itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can say the manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's something you cannot prevent.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, the pressures.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's being exerted because of which you feel it's something you cannot prevent.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, the body, depending on the nutrients that are nourishing the body somehow, it's something you cannot prevent.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot be eating nutrients and providing nutrients and saying, may these nutrients not nourish the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're nutrients because they nourish, because the body directly stands upon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the same principle, just a coarser, coarser form of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for the mind, which is subtler, it's again the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the mind would be inconceivable
[SPEAKER_01]: Without the natural manifestation upon which it stands, without name and form.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without that body, that form, and that mental capacity in regard to it, your mind would not be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you recognize that that body and the mental capacity in regard to it, the consciousness, that's not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's discovered through that determination that is the determination of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means the domain of those things,
[SPEAKER_01]: are inaccessible to you, the domain of nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_01]: The domain of pāsa is inaccessible to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, you cannot, no, experience the pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you can do is surmount it internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the fourth one is the origination of attention, that is the origination of phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the even subtler thing than your mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: The particular movements of your mind, the little jumps, the little sort of hooks, the directions, that's what attention is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, what does the attention depend on?
[SPEAKER_01]: Just the... Well, actually, so, what I said for the third, it's actually more accurately said for the fourth, the nature of manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can take nāmarūpa,
[SPEAKER_01]: What does nāmarūpa has as its nature?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's to manifest itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you take the nature of manifestation, what does correspond to it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of that, you can jump at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of that, you can direct towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when there is attending to something, when the attention is present, then what you have, through what you can discern through that attention is
[SPEAKER_01]: The thing has a reason, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: the arising is in you, the manifestation is there, of whatever, material or mental, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you can attend it, it's because it was given beforehand as an option to be attended to.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could not possibly move your attention
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you recognize, so me, moving my attention, it's completely secondary.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's only possible because this thing has arisen beforehand, because of which I'm attending to it right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that arising is something you're not saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, your attention, then, cannot be yours, because your attention cannot not depend on this random arising of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is there to attend then?
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you even think of attention?
[SPEAKER_01]: But, again, you could just take the first one, the course one.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, he just remains mindful of this body there, to the extent necessary for the final knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is just for different, basically different capacities, different people would have.
[SPEAKER_01]: For some people, pondering on the principle between attention and the manifestation that manifested through the attention, because of which attention is there in the first place, is quite a palpable thing to contemplate on, to keep in their mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for some people, it wouldn't be.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why he kind of laid out the principle in all like four gradually
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, increasing in subtlety, sort of, descriptions of the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if he only done it in terms of the body, then those people who were able to think in more subtle terms would see... well, mind you, they would figure it out themselves that it's the same principle, but the Buddha being, the Buddha Gautama being the one who's foremost in teaching the dhamma, would have expounded in every possible subtle way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, actually,
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, it comes to my mind, that other sutta in Digha Nikāya, the Buddha Vipassi, previous Buddha, the Buddha gives a story of him, whereby he, as a bodhisattva, discerned the principle of paticca-upāda, before he became a Buddha, and then, and then he starts describing it, vijjapācchā-saṅkāra, and so on, and then he comes to nāmarūpa determines the viññāṇa,
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, viññāṇa determines another rūpa.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where his pratītyapāda ended.
[SPEAKER_01]: He did not take it further into avijjā and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And says, but when he kind of finished sort of clarifying that formulation, then he remained mindful of the rising and falling of the manifestation of the five aggregates, of the experience as a whole, for for a period of time until his mind was fully
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could see that that Samasambuddha was not as detailed, as prolific as the Buddha in terms of defining the principle to all its possible subtleties.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the Buddha was.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's still the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, I'm saying, take up just the first paragraph that you read, and perfect that principle, develop it,
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, take it as far as you can, and it will result in your attention being freed from assumption in regard to manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a blanket, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, you have a particular disease, a particular bacteria attacking you, and you start giving a broad spectrum antibiotic that is not so strong.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to do it longer.
[SPEAKER_01]: But eventually, you will wipe out all the negative, all the harmful bacteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, if you're very accurate, if you have such capacity, you only get a very specific antibiotic that will very specifically kill only the harmful bacteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: But most people, it's not that black and white.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you kind of start with broad.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you might sort of narrow it down with more accurate treatment, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not necessarily.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't have access to it, just stick to the broad one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do it as long as necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it will destroy everything else that was supposed to be destroyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: It might sort of make you suffer a bit longer in terms of patience, enduring, and determination, and restraint, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not a big deal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it will kill you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Completely.